Meet Tony. He's my student.
قابلوا توني. انه طالبي.
He's about my age,
انه تقريبا بعمري ،
and he's in San Quentin State Prison.
وهو سجين في سجن سان كوينتين الحكومي.
When Tony was 16 years old,
عندما كان توني بعمر 16 عاما ،
one day, one moment,
يوم واحد ، لحظة واحدة،
"It was mom's gun.
"كانت بندقية أمي.
Just flash it, scare the guy. He's a punk.
فقط لوح بها ، ليخيف الرجل. انه فاسق.
He took some money; we'll take his money. That'll teach him.
أخذ بعض المال، ونحن سوف نأخذ ماله. هذا سيلقنه درسا.
Then last minute, I'm thinking, 'Can't do this. This is wrong.'
ثم في اللحظة الأخيرة ، أنا أفكر، "لا تفعل هذا. هذا خطأ. "
My buddy says, 'C'mon, let's do this.'
رفيقي يقول : "هيا ، دعنا نفعل هذا."
I say, 'Let's do this.'"
أقول ، "دعنا نفعل هذا."
And those three words, Tony's going to remember,
وهذه الكلمات الثلاث ، التي توني سيتذكرها ،
because the next thing he knows, he hears the pop.
لأن الشيء التالي انه يعرف انه يسمع موسيقى البوب.
There's the punk on the ground, puddle of blood.
هناك الفاسق على الأرض ، بركة من الدماء.
And that's felony murder --
وهذه جناية القتل --
25 to life, parole at 50 if you're lucky,
25 سنه إلى مدى الحياة ، والإفراج المشروط في 50 إذا كنت محظوظا،
and Tony's not feeling very lucky.
وتوني ليس محظوظ جدا.
So when we meet in my philosophy class in his prison
لذلك عندما نجتمع في درسي للفلسفة في سجنه
and I say, "In this class, we will discuss the foundations of ethics,"
وأنا أقول : "في هذا الدرس ، سنناقش أسس الأخلاق"
Tony interrupts me.
توني يقاطعني.
"What are you going to teach me about right and wrong?
"ماذا ستعلمني عن الصواب والخطأ؟
I know what is wrong. I have done wrong.
أنا أعرف ما هو الخطأ. لقد فعلت الخطأ.
I am told every day,
قيل لي كل يوم ،
by every face I see, every wall I face, that I am wrong.
من قبل كل وجه أراه ، كل جدار أواجه، أنا مخطئ.
If I ever get out of here, there will always be a mark by my name.
إذا أحصل وخرجت من هنا ، سيكون هناك دائما علامة على اسمي.
I'm a convict; I am branded 'wrong.'
أنا المحكوم عليه، وأنا الموصوف "بالخاطئ".
What are you going to tell me about right and wrong?"
ماذا ستقول لي عن الصواب والخطأ؟ "
So I say to Tony,
لذلك أنا أقول لتوني
"Sorry, but it's worse than you think.
"عذرا، لكنه أسوأ مما كنت اعتقد.
You think you know right and wrong?
كنت تعتقد انك تعرف الحق والباطل؟
Then can you tell me what wrong is?
ثم هل يمكنك أن تخبرني ما هو الخطأ؟
No, don't just give me an example.
لا ، لا تعطني مثالا فقط.
I want to know about wrongness itself, the idea of wrong.
أريد أن أعرف عن الخطيئة نفسها ، فكرة الـ خطأ.
What is that idea?
ما هي هذه الفكرة؟
What makes something wrong?
ما الذي يجعل شيئا ما خاطئا؟
How do we know that it's wrong? Maybe you and I disagree.
كيف نعرف أنه من الخطأ؟ ربما أنت وأنا لا أوافق.
Maybe one of us is wrong about the wrong.
ربما واحد منا مخطئاً عن ما هو الخطأ.
Maybe it's you, maybe it's me -- but we're not here to trade opinions;
ربما حان لكم ، ربما حان لي -- ولكن نحن لسنا هنا لتبادل لآراء؛
everyone's got an opinion.
كل واحد لديه رأي.
We are here for knowledge.
نحن هنا من أجل المعرفة.
Our enemy is thoughtlessness. This is philosophy."
عدونا هو عدم الإكتراث. هذه هي الفلسفة ".
And something changes for Tony.
و يتغير شيء ما لـ وتوني.
"Could be I'm wrong. I'm tired of being wrong.
"يمكن أن أكون مخطئا، وأنا تعبت من كوني خاطئ.
I want to know what is wrong.
أريد أن أعرف ما هو الخطأ.
I want to know what I know."
أريد أن أعرف ما أعرفه ".
What Tony sees in that moment is the project of philosophy,
ما يرى توني في تلك اللحظة هو مشروع الفلسفة ،
the project that begins in wonder --
المشروع الذي يبدأ في التساؤل --
what Kant called "admiration and awe
ما دعاه كانط "الإعجاب والرهبة
at the starry sky above and the moral law within."
في السماء المرصعة بالنجوم فوق القانون الأخلاقي في الداخل. "
What can creatures like us know of such things?
ماذا يمكن لمخلوقات مثلنا ان تعرف مثل هذه الأمور؟
It is the project that always takes us back to the condition of existence --
وهو المشروع الذي يأخذ دائما يعود بنا إلى حالة من الوجود --
what Heidegger called "the always already there."
ما يسميه هيدجر "دائما كان هناك بالفعل."
It is the project of questioning what we believe and why we believe it --
فمن المشروع التساؤل عما نؤمن به ونعتقد انه لماذا --
what Socrates called "the examined life."
ما دعاه سقراط بـ "الحياة المجربة".
Socrates, a man wise enough to know that he knows nothing.
سقراط، وهو رجل بلغ من الحكمة ما يكفي لمعرفة انه لا يعرف شيئا.
Socrates died in prison,
سقراط مات في السجن ،
his philosophy intact.
فلسفته سليمة.
So Tony starts doing his homework.
هكذا يبدأ توني القيام بواجباته المدرسية.
He learns his whys and wherefores, his causes and correlations,
انه يتعلم له أسبابه وحيثيات وأسبابه والعلاقات المتبادلة،
his logic, his fallacies.
له منطقه، مغالطاته.
Turns out, Tony's got the philosophy muscle.
تبين ، ان توني بنى عضلة فلسفية.
His body is in prison, but his mind is free.
جسده في السجن ، ولكن عقله حر.
Tony learns about the ontologically promiscuous,
توني يتعلم عن الوجودية،
the epistemologically anxious,
والحرص المعرفي،
the ethically dubious, the metaphysically ridiculous.
شكوك الأخلاقية، وسخافة الغيبي.
That's Plato, Descartes, Nietzsche
وهذا أفلاطون وديكارت ونيتشه
and Bill Clinton.
وبيل كلينتون.
So when he gives me his final paper,
حتى عندما يعطيني ورقته النهائية ،
in which he argues that the categorical imperative
والذي يقول إن ضرورة حتمية
is perhaps too uncompromising
ربما لا هوادة فيها للغاية
to deal with the conflict that affects our everyday
للتعامل مع الصراع الذي يؤثر على الحياة اليومية لدينا
and challenges me to tell him
والتحدي أن أقول له
whether therefore we are condemned to moral failure,
لذا كان محكوم علينا بالفشل الأخلاقي ،
I say, "I don't know.
وأقول : "أنا لا أعرف.
Let us think about that."
دعونا نفكر في ذلك ".
Because in that moment, there's no mark by Tony's name;
لأنه في تلك اللحظة، وليس هناك علامة بأسم توني؛
it's just the two of us standing there.
نحن مجرد اثنين نقف أمامها.
It is not professor and convict,
لسنا أستاذ و محكوم،
it is just two minds ready to do philosophy.
اننا مجرد عقلين على استعداد للتفلسف.
And I say to Tony,
و أقول لتوني
"Let's do this."
"دعونا نفعل هذا."
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)